Hello, and welcome to today's tutorial on image processing
In today's tutorial we'll be learning a very important function called thresholding
Thresholding, basically is used when we know the range in which the pixel value we need exists
and want to cut out the rest of the image
For example, in this image. let's say we want to display only the lion and to subtract the background
Let us see how to do that
In order to do that
Let us open fileImage.py and edit it
Let us first save this as threshimage.py
Now, we need to change the processing section
The first thing we need to do is convert this from an image that has BGR format into an image that is of a grayscale format
To do that we use the familiar command gray=cv2.cvtColor
Now the next thing we need to do is to threshold the image
In order to do that we use the command cv2.threshold
In this command, thresh1 is the new matrix in which the thresholded image is stored
and gray is the image that we are trying to do the threshold upon
150 is the value below which we want everything to turn black
and the things above 150 we want to make it white
In order to mae it white we must specify the value as 255
and finally the type of thresholding we are doing is binary
because in the resultant image there will be only 2 values
either 0 or 255
those pixels that have a value below 150 will be set to 0 and those pixels above will be set to 255
Now we need to show the output of this thresholding
So let us say
cv2.imshow, image as thresh1 and the image that we want to display as thresh1
and imag is the original image that we have
let us save this and see the output of this program
as you can see now we have this original image out of which the backround has been totally subtracted
because it is dark and only the lion is visible
Suppose we want to have more portion of the lion visible
that means we need to set our threshold lower
Let's see how we can do this
instead of 150 here I am going to givr an argument of 100
Let us save and see what happens
As you can see now more areas of the lion that were earlier darker are now visible
This is how thresholding works
that means that these pixels where it is white were above the value 100 and those that are black
are below the value 100
There are many different types of thresholding that are available to us through opencv
Let us see what they are
The first one as we have seen is THRESH_BINARY
The second one is called THRESH_BINARY_INV
where it inverts the value that we have chosen
Let me set the threshold to be the same so that we can compare all these kinds of thresholding
the third is called THRESH_TRUNC where it truncates the values that are below
and once above it least intact
the next type of thresholding is THRESH_TOZERO
and finally the fifth type is THRESH_TOZERO_INV
it is easier to see the output and understand what these individual kind of threshold do
than to explain them
so let's go ahead and see what they look like
In order to do that I must display all the output that are generated
so, therefore al I am going to do is copy paste this line and chaneg all the values
to the matrices that we want to display
which is thresh1,thresh2,thresh3,thresh4,thresh5
and accordingly display them in different windows
Alright, now let's see what the output of this program looks like
OK
As you can see now we have five different types of thresholdings
Firstly, this is the reference image that we have
This is the threshold that we have already seen which is binary
this is binary inverse
which is basically, just the opposite of binary
The next type of truncation that we see is trunct_zero
the next on is trunct_zero_inverse
and finally we have this
In order to recap,the kind of thresholds we have
are THRESH_BINARY
THRESH_BINARY_INV
THRESH_TRUNC
THRESH_TOZERO
and finally THRESH_TOZERO_INV
that's all for today's lecture. See you next time